A new standard of etiquette

Part of the goal of Algorithmic Rationalism is to introduce a new standard of etiquette to supplement pre-existing ones wherever the two are compatible and to supplant pre-existing ones on whatever matters they are at irreconcilable conflict.

There are plenty of codes of etiquette that exist int he world. Each one is generally written to serve various purposes, but rarely if ever is assuring the primacy of logic, reason, and evidence among those purposes. When it is, it tends to at times be overshadowed by other goals getting prioritized above it. Even codes of etiquette written expressly for the purpose of debate generally tend to strongly oppose rude or disorderly conduct, but have few if any portections against far more pernicious vices such as the use of deceptive rhetoric.

Granted, sometimes it can be difficult to include protections against such things in the debate's code of etiquette, as doing so might deter parties who wish to indulge in said unsavory behavior from participating in the debate. However, if the target audience of the debate were to strongly hold to a philosophy such as Algorithmic Rationalism, that might shift the scales of consideration in favor of including such provisions in the rules of the debate - as the credibility of the debate might rely on it. Similarly, it may in some cases even pressure a party that would otherwise be unwilling to participate in a debate in which logic, reason, and evidence have to actually be respected into doing so - or at least force them to openly expose unwillingness to try their views in the court of rationality.

In addition to merely asserting the importance of our codes of etiquette making logic, reason, and evidence a higher priority, part of the effort in developing Algorithmic Rationalism is the Rules of Discourse Project, whose sole publication currently is the Discursive Compendium of Fallacies and Malconducts. This document (currently an early work-in-progress, yet freely available as a Free Source project) strives to provide clear criteria for discerning whether or not a particular fallacy has been used, but also strives to describe what is and isn't proper conduct for debate, or any discussion, formal or informal, in a society that values rationality. It, too, does not intend to supplant pre-existing codes of etiquette - yet it does condemn invoking or enforcing those pre-existing codes in a manner that is at the expense of the unhindered pursuit of truth.

Basic Principles of Algorithmic Rationalism

Only one thing is sacrosanct in Algorithmic Rationalism, and that is the conviction that people ought to follow the dictates of logic, reason, and evidence wherever they lead. Consequently, there is only one thing that is taboo in Algorithmic Rationalism, and that taboo is to go against the one sacrosanct.

As for the methodologies used in Algorithmic Rationalism, the imperative to follow them is not a separate thing from the one sacrosanct, but an extension of it. This is because you are not truly following the dictates of logic, reason, and evidence wherever they lead if you violate the process by which these dictates are followed.

Very prominent among these methodologies is the one from which Algorithmic Rationalism derives its name - that being the use of razor algorithms to resolve matters of uncertainty in logic and reason. When it is uncertain whether or not a particular fallacy or malconduct has been committed, an algorithm can be devised whose outcome would indicate the answer to the uncertainty. These algorithms could range anywhere from a simple razor question to an elaborate tree of several razor questions.

Some such algorithms are contained in the Discursive Compendium of Fallacies and Malconducts - and while the algorithms there-contained are by no means guaranteed to be perfect, they do serve as a good example of how such algorithms ought to be drawn up.

While many people have come to think of algorithms as part of the world of computers (and often think of them as the nefarious constructs that internet media companies use to manipulate people) algorithms are not necessarily nefarious, nor are they necessarily tied to computers. These algorithms are not designed to be followed by computers at all, but by human beings who wish to come to as honest an understanding as possible with regards to the solidity of reason and discourse.

Expansion of what the term "logic" means

Algorithmic Rationalism also expands the idea of what logic is. Conventionally, logic is understood to be a study of how to go from a specific set of premises to a specific set of conclusions. No responsibility is taken for the accuracy of the conclusions of logic aside from them being accurate in the event (however hypothetical) that the premises are true.

Algorithmic Rationalism, however, refers to this area of study as "Hypothetical Logic" - and though we value it as a crucial part of the study of logic, we see the need to expand the understanding of what "logic" means to encompass also a separate area known as "Premise Theory". Premise Theory is the study of how to go about properly acquiring premises for use in logic as well as discerning what level of confidence to place in the premises thus derived. Granted - even Premise Theory can not guarantee the accuracy of the premises that one obtains or of the conclusions that are drawn from said premises. However, if Premise Theory is properly developed and then properly applied, it will nonetheless increase the level of reliability of the premises, even if not to the level of absolute certainty.

Such an expansion of what is understood by he term "logic" is no doubt bound to be controversial. Critics of such an expansion might contend that even if the study of Premise Theory must be undertaken, it shoudln't be regarded as part of the study of logic itself.

However, as controversial as it may be to expand the understanding of what "logic" means in such manner, this position is nonetheless defensible. Part of the reason for this expansion is because it is at long last catching-up the understanding of what "logic" means from one that is congruent with so-called "Continental Rationalism", the old style of Rationalism that eschews empiricism, with the more modern style of rationalism known as "English Rationalism" (despite not being at all exclusive to England or even the English-speaking world) which incorporates empiricism into rationalism. However, this congruity update is not the only reason for expanding this understanding of what "logic" means. It is also necessary because without the study of Premise Theory, the sound development of even Hypothetical Logic beyond the realm of its purely symbolic form can not be undertaken in a sound and useful manner.

Many scholars divide fallacies into two categories - formal and informal. Formal fallacies are flaws in an argument's structure that are reducable to a symbolic form. Informal fallacies, however, are flawed patterns of reasoning that generally aren't reducable to a form that can be expressed in the language of symbolic logic. When you are studying symbolic logic, the formal fallacies are the only fallacies that you have any need to be weary of. However, the moment you expand your study of logic beyond the purely symbolic realm, there immediately appears the need to be vigilant against informal fallacies in even the simplest of arguments.

And unlike with formal fallacies, it is very often impossible to distinguish an informal fallacy from a closely related cogency without resorting to the application of Premise Theory. For example, how else can you distinguish an instance of the False Dilemma Fallacy from an instance from the True Dilemma Cogency? How else can an instance of the Appeal to Consequences Fallacy be distinguished from a cogent form of inverse proof?

In theory one could suggest resolving such an issue by adding every ontological claim on which the cogency of an argument pattern hinges to the list of an argument's conditionals. However, in reality, if this were truly done with consistency, this would result in a practice so unwieldy that at best even a highly intelligent person would have difficulty practicing it in an ivory-tower setting - let alone a far cry from the goal of Algorithmic Rationalsim, which is a system that even ordinary people can learn to practice in everyday settings.

One might resolve this unwieldiness with the short cut of accepting ontological claims that the cogency of certain parts of the argument hinge on without adding them to the list of the argument's conditionals if said ontological claims are sufficiently obvious. This shotrt cut can seem irresistible considering how overwhelming a list of conditionals can become for even a relatively simple argument. However, such an acceptance of even the most obvious ontological claims without a methodology of doing so (i.e. Premise Theory) is a very self-deceptive practice that severely compromises the very integrity of one's study of logic.

It is much better to accept that any study of logic that ventures beyond the realm of mere symbolic logic must necessarily incorporate the study of Premise Theory.

Historical context of Algorithmic Rationalism

A few words are needed here of the historical context of our times, the times in which Algorithmic Rationalism was developed.

We are living in what is often referred to as a "post-truth society" - a society in which regard for whether or not an assertion conformed to objective reality is at dangerously low levels. As a matter of fact, regard for this is so low, that many people go so far as to dismiss its very existence - believing that the truth is whatever you can convince enough people of, or whatever you hold as a heartfelt belief. Not uncommon, as a matter of fact, is the belief that consciousness is a precursor of the material world rather than the other way around - a view that not only lacks regard for what exists in objective reality, but which outright denies its existence.

Of course - this view is scientifically unfathomable, but in a world that many people believe to be less than fifteen-thousand years old (typically just above six-thousand years old) despite overwhelming scientific evidence that it is actually a few billion years old - few people are going to let scientific unfathomability get in the way of what they wish to hold as doctrine.

Efforts to champion the existence of objective reality are often met with derision, with accusations of elitism. These accusations of elitism are often based partially on the perception that the one championing its existence believes zirself to have a complete knowledge of what is in that objective reality - or at least an understanding that is partial, yet authoritative. This perception is, of course, a straw-figure assertion - as championing that objective reality exists does not constitute asserting one's self as an infallible authority of its contents.

The Echo Chambers

In an environment in which the overwhelming majority of people have such disregard for objective reality, there is often no standard by which to resolve disagreements. Therefore, discussion on matters in which either side or both sides have high stakes or strong emotional vesture tend to devolve into blatant hostility. This hostility often escalates to the point that lines of communications between people who disagree are ruptured, forming enclaves of people whose commonality is defined by their agreement on certain issues. These enclaves are referred to commonly as "echo chambers".

In this environment, very few people still care for reason and evidence and sound discourse that values these things. A few people, however, do have regard for objective reality and do indeed care about these tools for investigating it. However, those people, too, tend to be trapped in echo chambers. These people wish to have rational dialogue on important subjects, but lack any partner with which to have such rational dialogue. Even though potential such partners exist, connecting with them can be difficult. Such Rationalists may attempt to hold open the channels of communication through which to communicate with fellow Rationalists of differeng sociopolitical persuasion - but run the risk of their good will being taken advantage by non-Rationalists who fail to discern the distinction between an invitation to rational dialogue versus an invitaion to launch an assault of rationally-empty rhetoric.

When the preservation of such channels is far more often used by those who seek to take the advantage of the good will behind them in effort to promote rhetoric than by fellow rationalists of differing sociopolitical persuasion who come for the genuine purpose of discussing the differences in persuasion in the same spirit for which the channels are kept open - the Rationalist is left with limited ways in which to respond.

Some Rationalists decide to engage the hostile visitor in debate the same way that they would debate a visitor of good will. This approach, however, can be extremely frustrating, and not particularly fruitful, as the Irrationalists lack the necessary regard or skills in logic and reason to present a convincing case by such means if they happen to be correct or to accept correction if such tools prove them to be in error. Debating them has been described as playing Chess with pigeons - the idea being that they knock over the pieces, defacate on the board, and then claim victory for themselves.

The maintainers of the channels of debate have responded to this abuse in various ways. Some of them have indulged in the mockery of debate up to the point of exhaustion, upon which they either let the propagandist present as victorious. At times, it has even been alleged that engaging a known distorter of logic and reason in debate even runs the risk of granting validation to a methodology of argument that deserves no such validation. The most notable recipient of this criticism is Bill Nye for his decision to participate in a debate against the Creationist, Ken Ham. However, surely Bill Nye is not the only one against whom such criticism could be directed.

Others have either directly shut down the channels of debate due to exhaustion responding to them being abused. Still others, while not directly shutting down the channels, effectively did so by declaring certain positions to be taboo. While it is difficult to judge them in any way sharshly for folding in such ways to such intense pressure, it would be better if they had a way to bann the underhanded means by which the propagandists advanced their views rather than to bann the views themselves.

The Post-Truth Society

We are living in what is often referred to as a "post-truth society" - a society in which regard for whether or not an assertion conformed to objective reality is at dangerously low levels. As a matter of fact, regard for this is so low, that many people go so far as to dismiss its very existence - believing that the truth is whatever you can convince enough people of, or whatever you hold as a heartfelt belief. Not uncommon, as a matter of fact, is the belief that consciousness is a precursor of the material world rather than the other way around - a view that not only lacks regard for what exists in objective reality, but which outright denies its existence.

Of course - this view is scientifically unfathomable, but in a world that many people believe to be less than fifteen-thousand years old (typically just above six-thousand years old) despite overwhelming scientific evidence that it is actually a few billion years old - few people are going to let scientific unfathomability get in the way of what they wish to hold as doctrine.

Efforts to champion the existence of objective reality are often met with derision, with accusations of elitism. These accusations of elitism are often based partially on the perception that the one championing its existence believes zirself to have a complete knowledge of what is in that objective reality - or at least an understanding that is partial, yet authoritative. This perception is, of course, a straw-figure assertion - as championing that objective reality exists does not constitute asserting one's self as an infallible authority of its contents.

This wonton disregard for objective reality has resulted in the shutdown of public discourse that has for a long time been regarded as essential to the democratic process. Granted, the process has always been flawed, having not only fallen short of perfection, but also fallen significantly short of what realistically ought to be the best possible for. But even those shortcomings were as a result of it having being hindered by the precursor of the very phenomena that in these days are shutting it down entirely - that being a disregard for objective reality that, though not always as extreme as it is today, has infected human history as far back as can be verified.

Part of this reason for the shutdown in public discourse is that, often, the two sides can no longer agree on any common basis for discussion. Without the acknowledgement of a common, objective reality, it is impossible for people of differing opinions to investigate what actually exists in that reality. As a result, the resolution of "agree to disagree", a resolution which in a sane society would be reserved only for disagreements whose resolution defies the current ability to resolve by investigation, is instead often lauded as the pinnacle of maturity for all disagreements, no matter how realistic it is to verify which of the statements, if any, is the correct one.

Therefore, instead of submitting to the authority of objective reality when an answer to the disagreement can be discovered, and "agreeing to disagree" when no answer can be discovered - the modus operandi has become to "agree to disagree" on matters for which stakes and emotional vesture are low, and sheer hostility when one or both sides has significant stakes or emotional vesture in their position.

When high stakes or emotional vesture cause someone to be so inflexible on their ideas as to cause this hostility, this decision is often justified either by fallacious reasoning that could be spotted a mile away by any well-trained Rationalist, or by an all-out dismissal of the importance of reason. This is done even if the opinion in question just so happens to be a correct one that could just as well have been backed by sound reason and evidence - because so low has the regard for objective reality sunk that such correct views are more frequently stumbled upon by sheer dumb luck than arrived at by the sound methodology of reason and evidence.

Relation to religion

As with most schools of Rationalism, the reigning theory on the God question is atheism. The existence of a Creator God is not seen as altogether impossible but as highly improbable - and of an Interventionist God even more imporbable.

That said - this reigning theory is not imposed as a requirement in Algorithmic Rationalism. On the other hand, this theory is not to be casually disregarded on the basis of some alternative being more emotionally satisfying, socially convenient, or politically convenient to believe. The actual position on how Algorithmic Rationalists ought to answer the God question is more nuanced than either of those two extremes.

There is only one sacrosanct in Algorithmic Rationalism - the commitment to follow the dictates of logic, reason, and evidence wherever they lead. This one sacrosanct does not contain any statement on theology. Not only does it not explicitly contain any statement on theology, but unlike the requirement to adhere to the methodologies of Algorithmic Rationalism, it isn't even implicitly in there.

That said - while this position of atheism is by no means an extension of the One Sacrosanct of Algorithmic Rationalism, we do believe it is the inevitable consequence of applying it to the God question. While terribly weak arguments for such a position (or even a more extreme position) do in fact exist, there are also some arguments for this position that are quite solid, are firmly backed by the weight of the evidence on the matter, and have sustained repeated checks. It may be possible for someone to apply the One Sacrosanct to the God question and a different answer - but it is extremely unlikely if the dictates of logic, reason, and evidence are truly followed in full.

That said - we wish to avoid a situation in which people blindly accept such an atheistic position simply because the community says that it is so. Also - even if we had incontrovertible proof that any perfect rationalist would embrace this atheistic position, we do not know anybody who is actually a perfect rationalist. Even the best of us are merely imperfect rationalists working on ourselves toward the goal of perfection. We would rather accept among us someone who genuinely attempts to follow the One Sacrosanct but who due to such imperfection lands on theism than someone who blindly accepts atheism simply because that's what the community says. Someone who lands on theism due to such an imperfection may have their theistic views challenged in the community in the form of people pointing out issues that they might have failed to consider - but they will be respected.

There is, however, one more reason why atheism is not a requirement for being regarded as an Algorithmic Rationalist. This is because there may be some people who have truly adopted Algorithmic Rationalism and are applying it to many areas of their life - but who for some reason haven't gotten around to, or simply aren't ready to apply it to the God question. They, too, are preferable to those who don't practice Rationalism at all but accept atheism for some reason other than logic, reason, or the weight of evidence.

Training to overcome irrational biases

One key goal in Algorithmic Rationalism is training ourselves to overcome our irrational biases. This is because no matter how much we learn to understand the process of Rationality in theory, and no matter how many exercises we do to hone this faculty, our irrational biases will constantly threaten to interfere with the process, and are liable to interfere without us even consciously realizing that this has happened.

It has been suggested that part of the means by which to do this on matters of social justice is to put yourself into the other person's sues - a practice of Cognitive Empathy. However, there is still the danger of our irrational biases tricking us into thinking that we have done this when in fact we haven't.

Overcoming your biases requires a lot of skills that are best honed both with exercises done on one's own and done in a community of Algorithmic Rationalists. We have to learn to check our biases - and that means, recognizing when they crop up, recognizing how they warp our thoughts, and administering the appropriate remedies to our thoughts.

All this requires that we know about the main viases that exist - and that each of us knows to which biases we are especially seceptible. We must know the warning signs of these biases - and we must develop algorithms for helping us better discern when one of these irrational biases is affecting our thoughts.

Very importantly, though, this process involves training in the art of true open-mindedness, which means, healthy skepticism of your own beliefs, whatever they are, and a willingness to modify them should evidence and reason dictate that it is appropriate to do so.